Guide to the Myron Carlos Burr Papers and memorabilia
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Myron Carlos Burr papers and memorabilia
1902-2006
1902-1946
SC0470
Burr, Myron Carlos, 1884-1977
5.5 Linear feet
Collection consists primarily of M. C. Burr's papers with a few items pertaining to his brother Walter and sister Gladys. Included are photographs, correspondence, clippings, typescripts of short articles, memorabilia from student days at Stanford University, and a scrapbook. The correspondence is largely Myron Burr?s letters to his family, 1905-08, but also includes Walter Burr?s letters to Gladys, and correspondence pertaining to the donation of these papers, 1971-2006. Subjects of the campus photographs include the Quad, Memorial Church, Encina dormitory rooms, club members on the porch of the Entre Nous eating club, athletics, and the laying of the last keystone in the outer Quad arcades. Student memorabilia includes registration and study cards, programs from campus events, several issues of the student newspaper, and dance cards. The scrapbook pertains to Burr?s career, Republican politics, flood control and water issues in the LA area (especially terracing hillsides as flood control), history of Monrovia, CA, and family events, 1918-42. Other items of note include his account of his experiences in San Francisco after the earthquake of 1906 and a record book kept while working for Shell Oil, Martinez refinery, 1916.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This materials are open for research use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Myron C. Burr earned his A.B. in civil engineering at Stanford University in May 1907. In the aftermath of the San Francisco Earthquake in 1906, he served with the Stanford Relief Corps and the San Francisco Water Commission. In addition to his career as a civil engineer, he ran an insurance agency specializing in industrial insurance, served on the Los Angeles County Emergency Relief Committee, wrote a newspaper column, and was a wholesale distributor of avocados. He was also active in the Republican Party in Southern California.
Description of the Collection
Collection consists primarily of M. C. Burr's papers with a few items pertaining to his brother Walter and sister Gladys. Included are photographs, correspondence, clippings, typescripts of short articles, memorabilia from student days at Stanford University, and a scrapbook. The correspondence is largely Myron Burr?s letters to his family, 1905-08, but also includes Walter Burr?s letters to Gladys, and correspondence pertaining to the donation of these papers, 1971-2006. Subjects of the campus photographs include the Quad, Memorial Church, Encina dormitory rooms, club members on the porch of the Entre Nous eating club, athletics, and the laying of the last keystone in the outer Quad arcades. Student memorabilia includes registration and study cards, programs from campus events, several issues of the student newspaper, and dance cards. The scrapbook pertains to Burr?s career, Republican politics, flood control and water issues in the LA area (especially terracing hillsides as flood control), history of Monrovia, CA, and family events, 1918-42. Other items of note include his account of his experiences in San Francisco after the earthquake of 1906 and a record book kept while working for Shell Oil, Martinez refinery, 1916.
Access Terms
Burr, Myron Carlos, 1884-1977; Burr, Walter Gordon.; Edwards, Patricia B.; Tresidder, Donald Bertrand, 1894-1948; Photoprints.; San Francisco Earthquake and Fire, Calif., 1906
Collection Contents
- Memorabilia, 1903-1975; Series 1
  - Big Game programs, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Civil Engineering Alumni Directory, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Daily Palo Alto, August, November, and December, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dance cards (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Earthquake reminiscences, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lyrics to prize-winning football songs, post 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Programs for various Stanford events, 1903-1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Registration and study cards (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Membership Certificate, American Arbitration Association, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Metal nameplate tag, M. C. Burr (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ink well damaged in San Francisco fire, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Cyanotype prints of Stanford scenes on one piece of silk [linen?]: Encina Hall, view of Memorial Church through Arches, Palm Drive, oblique view of Memorial Church, Memorial Arch, view down inner quad arcade, Roble Hall (Box 8)
  - Earthquake relief items mounted on paper (previously framed): Red ribbon "Stanford Relief"; Cloth with a red cross sewn on it; Pass signed by E. E. Schmitz, mayor; Instructions to Deputies, Relief Committee "Stanford Corps"; Student Relief Pass-Card issued to M. C. Burr; Instructions for Water Patrol Messengers and pass issued to M. C. Burr, as part of the Water Committee (Box 8)
- Photographs, 1903-1909; Series 2
  - Stanford scenes, includes dorm room scenes, excursion to "The Wunder" in Woodside, CA, campus buildings prior to the 1906 earthquake, ceremony at the laying of the last keystone in the outer Quad, club members on the porch of the Entrez Nous eating club, and male members of the Class of 1907 sitting on Encina steps, circa 1903-1906 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barbour, Le Roy W (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bateman, William George (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bell, Harry W. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bradley, F. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Burr, Clyde R. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Butterfield, Hayden Gearhart (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Campbell, Jesse Eugene (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fitting, Harold H. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Henley, Edward Vernon (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Irwin, Arthur M. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kip, Kathryn Romer (Mrs. Gerald A. Waring) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - McNeil, Warren Truett (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - O'Neale, Josiah Philip (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Porter, Arthur M. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ross, Perley A. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Taft, Harris W. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ward, Wendell W. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Waring, Gerald Ashley (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Unidentified students (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Unidentified people, F. C. Dando photographer (Los Angeles) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Photograph of Encina residents posed in front of Encina Hall [1911 Plug Ugly visible], circa 1909 (Box 2)
  - Photograph of Encina residents posed in front of Encina Hall [1910 Plug Ugly visible] (labeled ca. 1906 on reverse), circa 1908 (Box 2)
  - Photograph of Stanford Engineers, including Myron C. Burr (framed), 1907 (Box 2)
  - Photograph album of Myron C. Burr (SU scenes, student groups, Encina rooms, interior of Stanford power house, track events, football game, placing the last keystone in outer quad arcade, camping scenes (or possibly summer engineering job?), earthquake damage at SU), 1903-1906 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photograph album of Walter C. Burr [no earthquake images] (SU images, other CA places, excursions with friends, several images of Stanford student Sekko Shimada, Pres. T. Roosevelt on train in PA station, loading brandy barrel onto railroad car at Vina Ranch, M. C. Burr in his Encina room, other views of Encina rooms, Stanford track images) [some images appear in both albums], circa 1903-1906 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Papers, 1902-2006; Series 3
  - Biographical (career information) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Business memorabilia (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Certificates, 1919-1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Clippings (photocopied) re M. C. Burr, 1936-1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Original newsprint (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re donation of Stanford student hats, 2000-01 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Gladys Burr, notices re Stanford admission (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Photos of M. C. Burr, circa 1903-14 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photos, Burr Family (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Postcard correspondence, Stanford images, 1906-13, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Postcards to Clyde Burr, 1907-12 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Postcards to Myron C. Burr, 1906-07 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Postcards to Mr. & Mrs. F. W. Burr (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Postcards to Gladys Burr and Laura M. Burr, 1908, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous postcards (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - School memorabilia, MCB (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Stanford diploma, MCB's B.A., 1907 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Stanford Football Songs, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Turner, Maude E. – obituaries, photographs, and letter from Burr to his brother expressing his sorrow over her death, 1907-1908 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Record book kept while working for Shell Oil, Martinez refinery, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Calendar/Day book, 1908-1913 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook: clippings, articles, letters, brochures, pamphlets, and illustrations pertaining to Burr's career, Republican politics, flood control and water issues in LA area (especially terracing hillsides as flood control), history of Monrovia, CA, and family events. Also includes a brief letter from Herbert Hoover acknowledging receipt of Burr's pamphlet, 1933; photographs of Dalton Canyon, Dec. 8, 1934; and a blueprint "Sketch Plan of ditch location for Quesnelle Hydraulic Gold Mining Co. Burr & Fergusson, Engineers, Sept. 1909"., 1918-1985 (1918-1942 bulk) (Box 7)
  - Typescripts of M. C. Burr's writings:
    - Adventurer's Club (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Along the Way, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Arrowhead My First Engineering Job (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Dance Hall Girl (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Danger Spots (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - First Japanese Baseball Team [Stanford story] (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - First Night at a Nevada Gambling Resort, 1931, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Franklin Delano Roosevelt (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Greetings from One Columnist to Another, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - "Little Wads" Sunday School Class, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Mixed Pleasures of Frontier Travel, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Murl Emory, Kingfish of the Colorado (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Negro Porter, A (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "O! Ho! A Collection of Poems" by Burr, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - An Old Grad Goes to the Game [Stanford story] (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Phil Harris (with cover letter), 1962 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Phil Sullivan (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Plan to Conserve Mountain Water by Terracing (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Poems by M. C. Burr (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Politics (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - The Professor (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - The Reverend (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - San Francisco Fire and Earthquake, essay, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - San Quentin [Dr. Leo Stanley] (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - (Box 4, Folder 28)